<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sleep | Emma James</title>
    <link>/tag/sleep/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/sleep/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Sleep</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© Emma James 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Sleep</title>
      <link>/tag/sleep/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;ll be alright on the night</title>
      <link>/post/jcpp-2020-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/jcpp-2020-summary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sleep helps us to learn new words, but children with reading comprehension difficulties often have poor memory for new vocabulary. In our recent study, we asked whether their vocabulary problems lie in what happens during sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We taught children the names of unusual animals and plants. Some particular favourites were the shaggy &lt;em&gt;komondor&lt;/em&gt; dog and the rainbow &lt;em&gt;deglupta&lt;/em&gt; tree, pictured below&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The words were split across two sets of learning and test sessions. In one set children learned the new words first thing in the morning, and in the other set they learned the new words at the end of the evening. Straight after each learning session, they completed some memory tests for the words they had learned. Children then sat the same tests again 12 and 24 hours later, allowing us to trace how their memory changed over wake and sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;komondor.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Photo of a komondor dog&#34; style=&#34;width: 282px;&#34;/&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;deglupta.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Photo of a deglupta tree&#34; style=&#34;width: 200px;&#34;/&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Children were better at remembering the new words after they had slept. This memory boost lasted across the next day, even when children were tired again the following evening. Sleep was most beneficial when children learned the words right before their bedtime. In fact, when we visited again a month later, children were still better at remembering the words they had learned in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The children with reading comprehension difficulties found it harder to learn the new words. Even so, their memory still improved over sleep. Learning close to bedtime may be especially helpful for the children with a vocabulary weakness. Children with poor vocabulary were less likely to show sleep benefits for words learned earlier in the day. Nevertheless, all children showed sleep benefits for words learned in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So sleep is more than an opportunity for rest: it’s important for storing new words in long-term memory. Children with reading comprehension difficulties were equally able to benefit from sleep to retain their new knowledge, even though they found it harder to learn the words to start with. It may be that we can capitalise on sleep best if the information is fresh in our memory before we go to bed. This suggests that timing could play an important role in maximising learning – particularly for children with weaker vocabulary knowledge. For these children, a book at bedtime may be an especially valuable language learning opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was a summary of: Sleep-dependent consolidation in children with comprehension and vocabulary weaknesses: It’ll be alright on the night? James, Gaskell, &amp;amp; Henderson (2020), Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/jcpp.13253&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/jcpp.13253&lt;/a&gt; (open access)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image credits: Komondor: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Komondor_delvin.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nikki68&lt;/a&gt;; Deglupta: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/ucumari/29541867567&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Valerie&lt;/a&gt;; Front page image: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.publicdomainpictures.net/en/view-image.php?image=184718&amp;amp;picture=school-46&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Olivia Jester&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sleep-associated consolidation in app-based language learning</title>
      <link>/publication/memrise-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/memrise-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sleep-associated consolidation in app-based language learning</title>
      <link>/talk/07-20-cogsci/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/07-20-cogsci/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Puzzle of Vocabulary Growth</title>
      <link>/post/nbr-2017-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/nbr-2017-summary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Think about doing a jigsaw puzzle. Progress is often slow to begin with. It takes a while to work out how the thousands of tiny pieces fit within the bigger picture. A bit further down the line, you might have an outline. You&amp;rsquo;ve clustered some pieces together in their approximate space. The further you get in building the framework, the easier it becomes for you to place each individual piece. This phenomenon is true of learning new topics too &amp;mdash; we build cognitive frameworks that make it easier to learn related information. Yet, we don&amp;rsquo;t know much about how language learners use their prior knowledge. We asked, do children with better vocabulary knowledge find it easier to learn new words?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;featured.png&#34; width=&#34;200&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To look at this question, we re-analysed data from five experiments of word learning in children. Each experiment involved teaching children some made-up words (for example, &lt;em&gt;dolpheg&lt;/em&gt;) that were similar to real words in English (&lt;em&gt;dolphin&lt;/em&gt;). Researchers then tested whether the two words became integrated in vocabulary. The integration task measured how quickly the children could detect a short pause inserted into the real words (e.g., &lt;em&gt;dolph__in&lt;/em&gt;), to see whether the made-up words were competing for recognition. When a new word is integrated into vocabulary, response times slow down. The studies each found that sleep was important for this integration to happen: the new words interfered with children’s ability to process real words only when tested the next day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We re-analysed the data from these experiments to look at how word learning might depend on children&amp;rsquo;s prior knowledge. Children’s prior knowledge was assessed using a separate vocabulary test. We found that children with weak prior knowledge were less likely to embed new words into vocabulary overnight. Children with better prior knowledge were more likely to integrate new and known words. So what might be happening differently for these children overnight?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we first learn a new word, a region of the brain called the hippocampus creates a memory of it. It stores information about its sound, its meaning, and its connections to words we know. Those known words are stored in neocortical (outer) regions of the brain. During sleep, new memories are reorganised in the brain so that they too become part of this long-term knowledge. This is achieved by the hippocampus replaying and reactivating the new word memory. As a result, the connections between new and known words become stronger, and the new words become part of long-term vocabulary. We think that children with better prior knowledge can make more connections between new and known words during learning. With more connections, they experience bigger benefits from memory replay during sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Children who have a better language framework seem to more readily lay down each word “piece” of the language puzzle overnight. However, there are many reasons why children who do well at vocabulary assessments might also do well on these measures of word learning. Our research is trying to understand this relationship better. Which aspects of learning benefit most from prior knowledge? Do adults rely on prior knowledge more than children? How can this help us to understand atypical language development? I’ll be addressing these questions in the coming months. By better understanding how children use their existing knowledge during word learning, we hope to better understand why some children lag behind in vocabulary growth. Our finding that existing knowledge supports later &lt;em&gt;integration&lt;/em&gt; of new words into long-term memory tells us that the answer might lie beyond initial vocabulary instruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was a summary of: Consolidation of vocabulary during sleep: The rich get richer? James, Gaskell, Weighall, &amp;amp; Henderson (2017), Neuroscience &amp;amp; Biobehavioral Reviews. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.01.054&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.01.054&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A freely available version can be downloaded here: 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/113350/1/NBB_review_paper.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/113350/1/NBB_review_paper.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sleep‐dependent consolidation in children with comprehension and vocabulary weaknesses: it’ll be alright on the night?</title>
      <link>/publication/jcpp-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/jcpp-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From ZZZs to AAAs: Why Sleep Is an Important Part of Your Study Schedule</title>
      <link>/publication/fym-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/fym-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consolidation of vocabulary during sleep: the rich get richer?</title>
      <link>/publication/nbr-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/nbr-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
