<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Emma James</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© Emma James 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying difficulties in reading comprehension</title>
      <link>/project/poor-comprehenders/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/poor-comprehenders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Approximately 5-10% of children are thought to have difficulties with reading comprehension despite being able to read very accurately. Together with Jessie Ricketts, Danielle Colenbrander, Lisa Henderson, and Holly Joseph, we recently held a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/york.ac.uk/poor-comprehender-workshop/home&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;workshop to discuss research in this field&lt;/a&gt;. A key aim was to think about current practices for identifying children with specific reading comprehension difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following on from the workshop, we are combining data from previous projects to understand differences in measures of reading comprehension. We want to know whether currently used assessments for reading comprehension identify the same kinds of comprehension difficulties as previous measures, so that we can continue to build upon this research.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sleep-associated consolidation in app-based language learning</title>
      <link>/project/memrise-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/memrise-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Studies of word learning and consolidation have tempting practical implications. &lt;em&gt;Can we target sleep problems to help with learning difficulties? Might we remember information better if we sleep straight after learning it?&lt;/em&gt; However, our understanding of sleep and word learning mostly comes from lab experiments, which control lots of other things about the learning environment. This means that the benefits of sleep might not be as striking in real-world learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, I ask whether there is observable evidence for sleep-associated benefits in everyday language learning. Using app data from the foreign language-learning platform 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.memrise.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Memrise&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, we are testing whether memory for new words is better after a period of sleep compared to a period of wake. If it is, we can start to explore what else might support vocabulary learning in this context.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding memory processes across development</title>
      <link>/project/developmental-loops/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/developmental-loops/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The events we experience contain lots of different types of information, such as where we are, the people we are with, and the objects around us. These details are bound together in our memory for the event, making it easy for us to remember the different elements together. For example, we might experience going to the park with a relative and finding a lost handbag there, and later find we remember that story upon visiting the park again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a postdoc in the 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aidanhorner.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;York Episodic Memory Lab&lt;/a&gt;, I worked on a project trying to understand the processes that support this kind of memory, and how they change across development. We had to make some changes to the classic research tasks to make them child-friendly, which unintentionally ended up 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/pd9us/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;telling us a bit about the processes involved in itself&lt;/a&gt;! The developmental aspect of the study is still ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;project_logo.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Individual differences in word learning and consolidation</title>
      <link>/project/phd-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/phd-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My PhD research aimed to understand individual differences in word learning and consolidation. Why do some children find word learning harder than others, and what happens to word memories in the longer term? Together with 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.york.ac.uk/psychology/staff/academicstaff/lh/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Lisa Henderson&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.york.ac.uk/psychology/staff/academicstaff/mgg5/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Professor Gareth Gaskell&lt;/a&gt;, we looked at how word learning might build on existing vocabulary knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We approached this question in three main ways. First, we looked at how individuals&amp;rsquo; existing vocabulary knowledged predicted their ability to learn and consolidate new words. Second, we manipulated the ways in which new words could relate to prior knowledge, and looked at how it affected word learning success. Third, we looked at children who often find word learning difficult, as is characteristic of children with reading comprehension difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The role of morphological awareness in reading comprehension</title>
      <link>/project/ma-lancaster/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/ma-lancaster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After completing my undergraduate degree, I worked on an ESRC-funded project on the relations between morphological awareness and reading comprehension, led by Professor Kate Cain (Lancaster University) and Professor Xiuli Tong (The University of Hong Kong). You can find out about this project here: 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psych.lancs.ac.uk/esrc-morphology/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.psych.lancs.ac.uk/esrc-morphology/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
