<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Emma James</title>
    <link>/author/emma-james/</link>
      <atom:link href="/author/emma-james/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Emma James</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© Emma James 2020</copyright>
    <image>
      <url>/author/emma-james/avatar_hu6d1266e2390aaa751830d5f758ea3c18_2010968_270x270_fill_q90_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Emma James</title>
      <link>/author/emma-james/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools and tips for collecting spoken responses online</title>
      <link>/post/online-voice-recordings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/online-voice-recordings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I gave a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/06-20-beonline/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; on running multi-session studies online at the 2020 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://beonline.research.sc/2020&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BeOnline conference&lt;/a&gt;. I mentioned that we had recently collected vocal responses online, but that I didn’t have time to talk about it. So, here’s a little bit more about my experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We collected spoken responses as part of a word learning study. 125 participants were recruited via Prolific, and listened to a spoken story containing made-up words. In each of three test sessions (same day, next day, one week later), we asked them to try and recall the made-up words. We presented them with the starting sound for each word, and asked them to try and speak the whole word that they had heard in the story. We were interested in which words participants could remember at each test point, scoring each trial as correct or incorrect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tools&#34;&gt;The tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experiment was programmed in Gorilla, and we collected spoken responses using the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gorilla.sc/support/reference/task-builder-zones#audiorecordingbeta&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;“Audio Recording Zone”&lt;/a&gt;. This zone is still in BETA testing (at the time of posting), which means that Gorilla are still ironing out a few issues. We did some thorough piloting and made it through relatively problem-free, but Gorilla have added some warnings of issues to be aware of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The zone includes a “Test Mode” option, which is Gorilla’s built-in tool for participants to test whether their microphones are working. This mode creates a short recording of the participant’s voice and plays it back to them so that they can check they can be heard. Note that this relies on their honesty though &amp;ndash; there is no way for the software itself to check sound quality, or for you to know that recordings are OK before the participant proceeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within your experimental task, you incorporate the zone on the relevant trial screen as you would any other response zone in Gorilla, and set the option to “Record Mode”. This will record a short sound file for each trial, which can be ended by a button press or a timeout (you can see the various setting options in the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gorilla.sc/support/reference/task-builder-zones#audiorecordingbeta&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt;). At the end of my experiment, I downloaded a short .mp3 file for each word trial for each participant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.3758/BF03192979&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CheckVocal&lt;/a&gt; (Protopapas, 2007) for scoring each recording as correct or incorrect. CheckVocal is freely available software that was originally designed to process naming data from DMDX software. Although these recordings were collected via Gorilla, it still did the job for me (after converting the files to .wav first). You can download the software from 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/0avasns/CheckVocal&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tips&#34;&gt;The tips&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, so I’ve only run one experiment &amp;ndash; I don’t have a HUGE wealth of knowledge to offer. But here are the steps I took (or would take next time!) to try and maintain data quality:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Put a test mode at the very start of your experiment.&lt;/strong&gt; I put this even before the main study information and consent form, as no data is collected at this stage.  Ask participants to change their settings until their audio is clear. If they can’t get it to work, they can return to Prolific with very little time lost, thereby minimising expensive data loss for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repeat the test mode&lt;/strong&gt; before the recording part of your task. You might not need to do this, but I repeated the recording tasks in subsequent test sessions and wanted to provide an opportunity for re-adjustment if needed. Plus it doesn’t harm to be a little extra cautious!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create your own test recording.&lt;/strong&gt; The test modes don’t store any data for you, so I added my own test trial. I asked participants to speak “Take me to the task” before starting the experiment, which served three main purposes:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It gave me a quick reference trial to check before approving the participant&amp;rsquo;s submission on Prolific. Checking data quality before approval provides an opportunity to query any issues  at a stage when participants are likely to respond.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It provided a reference trial for subsequent scoring. Blank sound files are very hard to interpret (see below), so evidence of the participant’s microphone working during that test session can be helpful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It reinforced that sound recording was a vital part of the experiment, and that participants shouldn’t try to proceed without it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;(And an extra point – it was wonderful listening to all the kind strangers with their various accents asking to be taken to the experiment!)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid blank sound files.&lt;/strong&gt; Empty recordings can be very hard to interpret: they tend to consist of only white noise, and/or might be very short. This leaves you with no idea whether the participant didn’t attempt a response or whether the recording didn&amp;rsquo;t work properly. To help with this, we encouraged participants to attempt an answer if they could, and speak “don’t know” or “pass” if not. The majority of participants did this, but I think in future I would keep a reminder on-screen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t expect a lab-based environment.&lt;/strong&gt; Before starting this experiment, I had an idealised view that I would be able to tell if a participant wasn’t in an appropriately quiet environment, and that it would be easy to exclude them on that basis. It isn’t. You have no real idea whether that faint music/television is in the same room and whether the participants can hear it through their headphones. You don’t know how distracted that participant is from the children screaming at each other (OK I might have had to exclude &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; trial…). You might even hear your participants take an extra moment to ask their co-habitant to be quiet. Then what?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;…Think very carefully about the implications of background noise for your research question&lt;/strong&gt;, and remember that you will never have the same control as in the lab. This goes for any online study &amp;mdash; it just becomes more obvious when collecting sound recordings. Of course, you will ask that your participants are in a quiet environment where they are unlikely to be disturbed, but if this is crucial to your experiment then you will really need to spell out exactly what that means and think through your criteria for exclusion. For me, my main measure was the accuracy of the word remembered (response times didn&amp;rsquo;t matter) and I had other ways to ensure that participants were engaging with the task. I was also comparing this experiment to one conducted with children in schools &amp;ndash; background noise and screaming children are pretty common occurrences there too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that’s all I can think of that might be helpful, but please feel free to leave comments with any further questions or your own tips and experiences. You can read more about the study in our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/vm5ad&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;recent preprint&lt;/a&gt;, or access the experimental tasks on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gorilla.sc/openmaterials/104397&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gorilla Open Materials&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy data collection!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The role of prior lexical knowledge in children’s and adults’ word learning from stories</title>
      <link>/publication/storyneighb-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/storyneighb-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sleep-associated consolidation in app-based language learning</title>
      <link>/publication/memrise-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/memrise-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sleep-associated consolidation in app-based language learning</title>
      <link>/talk/07-20-cogsci/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/07-20-cogsci/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The relations between morphological awareness and reading comprehension in beginner readers to young adolescents</title>
      <link>/publication/jrir-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/jrir-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A (half) marathon not a sprint: Preparing to conduct multi-session memory studies online</title>
      <link>/talk/06-20-beonline/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/06-20-beonline/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open research means open conversation</title>
      <link>/talk/06-20-yor/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/06-20-yor/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Puzzle of Vocabulary Growth</title>
      <link>/post/nbr-2017-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/nbr-2017-summary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Think about doing a jigsaw puzzle. Progress is often slow to begin with. It takes a while to work out how the thousands of tiny pieces fit within the bigger picture. A bit further down the line, you might have an outline. You&amp;rsquo;ve clustered some pieces together in their approximate space. The further you get in building the framework, the easier it becomes for you to place each individual piece. This phenomenon is true of learning new topics too &amp;mdash; we build cognitive frameworks that make it easier to learn related information. Yet, we don&amp;rsquo;t know much about how language learners use their prior knowledge. We asked, do children with better vocabulary knowledge find it easier to learn new words?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;featured.png&#34; width=&#34;200&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To look at this question, we re-analysed data from five experiments of word learning in children. Each experiment involved teaching children some made-up words (for example, &lt;em&gt;dolpheg&lt;/em&gt;) that were similar to real words in English (&lt;em&gt;dolphin&lt;/em&gt;). Researchers then tested whether the two words became integrated in vocabulary. The integration task measured how quickly the children could detect a short pause inserted into the real words (e.g., &lt;em&gt;dolph__in&lt;/em&gt;), to see whether the made-up words were competing for recognition. When a new word is integrated into vocabulary, response times slow down. The studies each found that sleep was important for this integration to happen: the new words interfered with children’s ability to process real words only when tested the next day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We re-analysed the data from these experiments to look at how word learning might depend on children&amp;rsquo;s prior knowledge. Children’s prior knowledge was assessed using a separate vocabulary test. We found that children with weak prior knowledge were less likely to embed new words into vocabulary overnight. Children with better prior knowledge were more likely to integrate new and known words. So what might be happening differently for these children overnight?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we first learn a new word, a region of the brain called the hippocampus creates a memory of it. It stores information about its sound, its meaning, and its connections to words we know. Those known words are stored in neocortical (outer) regions of the brain. During sleep, new memories are reorganised in the brain so that they too become part of this long-term knowledge. This is achieved by the hippocampus replaying and reactivating the new word memory. As a result, the connections between new and known words become stronger, and the new words become part of long-term vocabulary. We think that children with better prior knowledge can make more connections between new and known words during learning. With more connections, they experience bigger benefits from memory replay during sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Children who have a better language framework seem to more readily lay down each word “piece” of the language puzzle overnight. However, there are many reasons why children who do well at vocabulary assessments might also do well on these measures of word learning. Our research is trying to understand this relationship better. Which aspects of learning benefit most from prior knowledge? Do adults rely on prior knowledge more than children? How can this help us to understand atypical language development? I’ll be addressing these questions in the coming months. By better understanding how children use their existing knowledge during word learning, we hope to better understand why some children lag behind in vocabulary growth. Our finding that existing knowledge supports later &lt;em&gt;integration&lt;/em&gt; of new words into long-term memory tells us that the answer might lie beyond initial vocabulary instruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was a summary of: Consolidation of vocabulary during sleep: The rich get richer? James, Gaskell, Weighall, &amp;amp; Henderson (2017), Neuroscience &amp;amp; Biobehavioral Reviews. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.01.054&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.01.054&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A freely available version can be downloaded here: 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/113350/1/NBB_review_paper.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/113350/1/NBB_review_paper.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sleep‐dependent consolidation in children with comprehension and vocabulary weaknesses: it’ll be alright on the night?</title>
      <link>/publication/jcpp-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/jcpp-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From ZZZs to AAAs: Why Sleep Is an Important Part of Your Study Schedule</title>
      <link>/publication/fym-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/fym-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Make or break it: Boundary conditions for integrating multiple elements in episodic memory</title>
      <link>/publication/breakdep-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/breakdep-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Offline consolidation supersedes prior knowledge benefits in children&#39;s (but not adults&#39;) word learning</title>
      <link>/publication/devsci-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/devsci-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consolidating new words from repetitive versus multiple stories: Prior knowledge matters</title>
      <link>/publication/jecp-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/jecp-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consolidation of vocabulary during sleep: the rich get richer?</title>
      <link>/publication/nbr-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/nbr-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Commentary: Knowledge Acquisition during Exam Preparation Improves Memory and Modulates Memory Formation</title>
      <link>/publication/fbn-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/fbn-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
