<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Emma James</title>
    <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/author/emma-james/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.emma-james.co.uk/author/emma-james/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Emma James</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© Emma James 2023</copyright>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/author/emma-james/avatar_hu6d1266e2390aaa751830d5f758ea3c18_2010968_270x270_fill_q90_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Emma James</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/author/emma-james/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heterogeneity in children’s reading comprehension difficulties: a latent class approach</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/heterocomp-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/heterocomp-2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Word learning in the context of semantic prior knowledge: Evidence of interference from feature-based neighbours in children and adults</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/semneighb-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/semneighb-2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gorilla Presents... Speech Production Research Online</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/04-21-gorilla-speech/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/04-21-gorilla-speech/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The role of prior lexical knowledge in children’s and adults’ incidental word learning from illustrated stories</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/storyneighb-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/storyneighb-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The formation and retrieval of holistic event memories across development</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/devdep-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/devdep-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Word learning through the lens of prior knowledge</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/01-21-eps-frith/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/01-21-eps-frith/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;ll be alright on the night? Exploring bedtime benefits for vocabulary learning</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/11-20-ucl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/11-20-ucl/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From little to large: the importance of understanding morphemes for understanding texts</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/post/jrir-2020-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/post/jrir-2020-summary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you can bear to read the news at the moment, you will likely come across words you had no reason to encounter before 2020. How is it that we can so readily skim over new terms such as &lt;em&gt;maskless&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;super-spreader&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;pre-lockdown&lt;/em&gt;? Well, these words are each built from smaller units of meaning called morphemes. We know that &lt;em&gt;–less&lt;/em&gt; means “without”, adding &lt;em&gt;–er&lt;/em&gt; refers to a person that does something, and &lt;em&gt;pre-&lt;/em&gt; means “before”. This awareness of morphemes can help us understand language even when words are unfamiliar. Thus, morphological awareness likely helps developing readers as they face increasingly challenging texts. We put this proposal to the test in our recent study of reading comprehension in 6- to 13-year-old children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We designed six tasks to assess three different types of morphology: compounds, inflections, and derivations (described in the table below). We assessed awareness of each type in two ways. In one task, children chose the most appropriate transformation between options. In the other, children produced a morphological transformation themselves. The tasks included both real and made-up words, to make sure they were measuring more than just vocabulary knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;img src=&#34;task_table.png&#34; alt=&#34;Tasks used to assess different types of morphology&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across all three age groups (6-8 years, 9-11 years, 12-13 years), children’s morphological awareness scores were strongly related to their reading comprehension ability. The crucial test was to see whether morphological awareness explained differences in reading comprehension over and above other important skills, such as phonological awareness (the ability to isolate and manipulate sounds in words), vocabulary, nonverbal reasoning, and reading accuracy. For the 6-8 and 12-13 year olds, we found that morphological awareness further improved the prediction of reading comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was also some indication that morphological awareness was particularly important for children with weak comprehension, whereas vocabulary was a stronger predictor for good comprehenders. However, these differences were small and not clear-cut. All in all, both morphological awareness &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; vocabulary played important roles in reading comprehension across the spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this study shows that morphological awareness does have a unique role to play in reading comprehension: it adds something more to comprehension ability than the skills we typically measure in the classroom. Importantly, it predicts reading comprehension from beginning readers to adolescents, and across a wide range of abilities. This finding illustrates the importance of incorporating morphology instruction throughout literacy development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was a summary of: The relations between morphological awareness and reading comprehension in beginner readers to young adolescents. James, Currie, Tong, &amp;amp; Cain (2020), Journal of Research in Reading. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/1467-9817.12316&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/1467-9817.12316&lt;/a&gt; (open access)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Make or break it: Boundary conditions for integrating multiple elements in episodic memory</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/breakdep-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/breakdep-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When the wabon flew to the intergalatic zoo: Accessing prior lexical knowledge in explicit and incidental word learning</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/09-20-llc-rhul/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2020 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/09-20-llc-rhul/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using prior knowledge to build vocabulary</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/post/devsci-2019-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/post/devsci-2019-summary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Children with good literacy skills are more likely to enjoy reading, read more texts of increasing difficulty, and learn more words as a result. This snowballing literacy development is known as the &lt;em&gt;Matthew effect&lt;/em&gt;. While the rich in vocabulary knowledge get richer, children with poor vocabulary fall increasingly far behind. Yet differences in word learning are not only seen in reading contexts. We asked how a learner&amp;rsquo;s existing vocabulary might help them to &lt;em&gt;remember&lt;/em&gt; new words. We found that children and adults both used their prior knowledge to help them learn new words, but that children might be better placed to overcome any limitations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test the role of prior knowledge, we taught participants made-up words with different numbers of “neighbours” in English. A word is a neighbour if it involves a single sound swap. For example, the made-up word &lt;em&gt;solly&lt;/em&gt; has neighbours in &lt;em&gt;silly, jolly, sally, folly,&lt;/em&gt; etc. We predicted that prior knowledge of neighbours would help in learning made-up words. In contrast, the made-up word &lt;em&gt;peflin&lt;/em&gt; has no neighbours in English, making it harder for people to use their prior knowledge to help. After learning the new words, we tested participants’ ability to remember them when prompted with the starting sounds. Could people recall &lt;em&gt;peflin&lt;/em&gt; given only &lt;em&gt;pe-&lt;/em&gt;? Participants completed the same memory task the next day and one week later. These later tests were important because sleep can improve memory for new words, and changes how they are stored in long-term vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immediately after learning, people were much better at remembering words with neighbours. This means that both children and adults use their prior knowledge to help them learn. Intriguingly, it was the words &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; neighbours that improved the most across tests. Moreover, children improved more than adults, so they were equally good at remembering words with and without neighbours one week later.  This fits with the idea that children’s memory might benefit more from sleep compared to adults (although sleep is only one possible explanation, since we didn’t measure sleep itself in this study). A better ability to improve new memories is helpful for children, as they typically have lots of new information to learn and less prior knowledge to help them learn it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also measured children’s and adults’ existing vocabulary knowledge using a separate assessment. We predicted that individuals with good vocabulary would know more word neighbours, and show a bigger benefit from them in learning. This was not the case. Those with better vocabulary remembered more words overall, but the benefit was not specific to words with neighbours. In later experiments, we found that one neighbour was enough to help a new word in memory. Perhaps, then, all children and adults could access one of the many possible neighbours in our study to help them learn, but it did not help to know more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So prior knowledge helped memory for new words, but could not account for the Matthew effect in vocabulary learning for two reasons. First, individuals with better vocabulary learned more words regardless of their neighbours. Second, the benefit from neighbours was short-lived, especially for children. Other, possibly sleep-related, processes helped words that could not benefit from prior knowledge to catch up in memory. This was particularly the case for children, and likely helps to support the vast amounts of new learning during childhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was a summary of: Offline consolidation supersedes prior knowledge benefits in children&amp;rsquo;s (but not adults&amp;rsquo;) word learning. James, Gaskell, &amp;amp; Henderson (2019), Developmental Science. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/desc.12776&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/desc.12776&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An open access version is available 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/139458/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learn, Sleep, Recall, Repeat</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/08-20-memtalk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/08-20-memtalk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;ll be alright on the night</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/post/jcpp-2020-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/post/jcpp-2020-summary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sleep helps us to learn new words, but children with reading comprehension difficulties often have poor memory for new vocabulary. In our recent study, we asked whether their vocabulary problems lie in what happens during sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We taught children the names of unusual animals and plants. Some particular favourites were the shaggy &lt;em&gt;komondor&lt;/em&gt; dog and the rainbow &lt;em&gt;deglupta&lt;/em&gt; tree, pictured below&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The words were split across two sets of learning and test sessions. In one set children learned the new words first thing in the morning, and in the other set they learned the new words at the end of the evening. Straight after each learning session, they completed some memory tests for the words they had learned. Children then sat the same tests again 12 and 24 hours later, allowing us to trace how their memory changed over wake and sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;komondor.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Photo of a komondor dog&#34; style=&#34;width: 282px;&#34;/&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;deglupta.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Photo of a deglupta tree&#34; style=&#34;width: 200px;&#34;/&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Children were better at remembering the new words after they had slept. This memory boost lasted across the next day, even when children were tired again the following evening. Sleep was most beneficial when children learned the words right before their bedtime. In fact, when we visited again a month later, children were still better at remembering the words they had learned in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The children with reading comprehension difficulties found it harder to learn the new words. Even so, their memory still improved over sleep. Learning close to bedtime may be especially helpful for the children with a vocabulary weakness. Children with poor vocabulary were less likely to show sleep benefits for words learned earlier in the day. Nevertheless, all children showed sleep benefits for words learned in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So sleep is more than an opportunity for rest: it’s important for storing new words in long-term memory. Children with reading comprehension difficulties were equally able to benefit from sleep to retain their new knowledge, even though they found it harder to learn the words to start with. It may be that we can capitalise on sleep best if the information is fresh in our memory before we go to bed. This suggests that timing could play an important role in maximising learning – particularly for children with weaker vocabulary knowledge. For these children, a book at bedtime may be an especially valuable language learning opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was a summary of: Sleep-dependent consolidation in children with comprehension and vocabulary weaknesses: It’ll be alright on the night? James, Gaskell, &amp;amp; Henderson (2020), Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/jcpp.13253&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/jcpp.13253&lt;/a&gt; (open access)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image credits: Komondor: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Komondor_delvin.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nikki68&lt;/a&gt;; Deglupta: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/ucumari/29541867567&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Valerie&lt;/a&gt;; Front page image: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.publicdomainpictures.net/en/view-image.php?image=184718&amp;amp;picture=school-46&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Olivia Jester&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools and tips for collecting spoken responses online</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/post/online-voice-recordings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/post/online-voice-recordings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I gave a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/06-20-beonline/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; on running multi-session studies online at the 2020 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://beonline.research.sc/2020&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BeOnline conference&lt;/a&gt;. I mentioned that we had recently collected vocal responses online, but that I didn’t have time to talk about it. So, here’s a little bit more about my experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We collected spoken responses as part of a word learning study. 125 participants were recruited via Prolific, and listened to a spoken story containing made-up words. In each of three test sessions (same day, next day, one week later), we asked them to try and recall the made-up words. We presented them with the starting sound for each word, and asked them to try and speak the whole word that they had heard in the story. We were interested in which words participants could remember at each test point, scoring each trial as correct or incorrect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tools&#34;&gt;The tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experiment was programmed in Gorilla, and we collected spoken responses using the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gorilla.sc/support/reference/task-builder-zones#audiorecordingbeta&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;“Audio Recording Zone”&lt;/a&gt;. This zone is still in BETA testing (at the time of posting), which means that Gorilla are still ironing out a few issues. We did some thorough piloting and made it through relatively problem-free, but Gorilla have added some warnings of issues to be aware of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The zone includes a “Test Mode” option, which is Gorilla’s built-in tool for participants to test whether their microphones are working. This mode creates a short recording of the participant’s voice and plays it back to them so that they can check they can be heard. Note that this relies on their honesty though &amp;ndash; there is no way for the software itself to check sound quality, or for you to know that recordings are OK before the participant proceeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within your experimental task, you incorporate the zone on the relevant trial screen as you would any other response zone in Gorilla, and set the option to “Record Mode”. This will record a short sound file for each trial, which can be ended by a button press or a timeout (you can see the various setting options in the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gorilla.sc/support/reference/task-builder-zones#audiorecordingbeta&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt;). At the end of my experiment, I downloaded a short .mp3 file for each word trial for each participant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.3758/BF03192979&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CheckVocal&lt;/a&gt; (Protopapas, 2007) for scoring each recording as correct or incorrect. CheckVocal is freely available software that was originally designed to process naming data from DMDX software. Although these recordings were collected via Gorilla, it still did the job for me (after converting the files to .wav first). You can download the software from 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/0avasns/CheckVocal&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tips&#34;&gt;The tips&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, so I’ve only run one experiment &amp;ndash; I don’t have a HUGE wealth of knowledge to offer. But here are the steps I took (or would take next time!) to try and maintain data quality:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Put a test mode at the very start of your experiment.&lt;/strong&gt; I put this even before the main study information and consent form, as no data is collected at this stage.  Ask participants to change their settings until their audio is clear. If they can’t get it to work, they can return to Prolific with very little time lost, thereby minimising expensive data loss for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repeat the test mode&lt;/strong&gt; before the recording part of your task. You might not need to do this, but I repeated the recording tasks in subsequent test sessions and wanted to provide an opportunity for re-adjustment if needed. Plus it doesn’t harm to be a little extra cautious!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create your own test recording.&lt;/strong&gt; The test modes don’t store any data for you, so I added my own test trial. I asked participants to speak “Take me to the task” before starting the experiment, which served three main purposes:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It gave me a quick reference trial to check before approving the participant&amp;rsquo;s submission on Prolific. Checking data quality before approval provides an opportunity to query any issues  at a stage when participants are likely to respond.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It provided a reference trial for subsequent scoring. Blank sound files are very hard to interpret (see below), so evidence of the participant’s microphone working during that test session can be helpful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It reinforced that sound recording was a vital part of the experiment, and that participants shouldn’t try to proceed without it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;(And an extra point – it was wonderful listening to all the kind strangers with their various accents asking to be taken to the experiment!)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid blank sound files.&lt;/strong&gt; Empty recordings can be very hard to interpret: they tend to consist of only white noise, and/or might be very short. This leaves you with no idea whether the participant didn’t attempt a response or whether the recording didn&amp;rsquo;t work properly. To help with this, we encouraged participants to attempt an answer if they could, and speak “don’t know” or “pass” if not. The majority of participants did this, but I think in future I would keep a reminder on-screen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t expect a lab-based environment.&lt;/strong&gt; Before starting this experiment, I had an idealised view that I would be able to tell if a participant wasn’t in an appropriately quiet environment, and that it would be easy to exclude them on that basis. It isn’t. You have no real idea whether that faint music/television is in the same room and whether the participants can hear it through their headphones. You don’t know how distracted that participant is from the children screaming at each other (OK I might have had to exclude &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; trial…). You might even hear your participants take an extra moment to ask their co-habitant to be quiet. Then what?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;…Think very carefully about the implications of background noise for your research question&lt;/strong&gt;, and remember that you will never have the same control as in the lab. This goes for any online study &amp;mdash; it just becomes more obvious when collecting sound recordings. Of course, you will ask that your participants are in a quiet environment where they are unlikely to be disturbed, but if this is crucial to your experiment then you will really need to spell out exactly what that means and think through your criteria for exclusion. For me, my main measure was the accuracy of the word remembered (response times didn&amp;rsquo;t matter) and I had other ways to ensure that participants were engaging with the task. I was also comparing this experiment to one conducted with children in schools &amp;ndash; background noise and screaming children are pretty common occurrences there too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that’s all I can think of that might be helpful, but please feel free to leave comments with any further questions or your own tips and experiences. You can read more about the study in our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/vm5ad&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;recent preprint&lt;/a&gt;, or access the experimental tasks on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gorilla.sc/openmaterials/104397&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gorilla Open Materials&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy data collection!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sleep-associated consolidation in app-based language learning</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/memrise-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/memrise-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sleep-associated consolidation in app-based language learning</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/07-20-cogsci/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/07-20-cogsci/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The relations between morphological awareness and reading comprehension in beginner readers to young adolescents</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/jrir-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/jrir-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A (half) marathon not a sprint: Preparing to conduct multi-session memory studies online</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/06-20-beonline/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/06-20-beonline/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open research means open conversation</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/06-20-yor/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/talk/06-20-yor/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Puzzle of Vocabulary Growth</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/post/nbr-2017-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/post/nbr-2017-summary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Think about doing a jigsaw puzzle. Progress is often slow to begin with. It takes a while to work out how the thousands of tiny pieces fit within the bigger picture. A bit further down the line, you might have an outline. You&amp;rsquo;ve clustered some pieces together in their approximate space. The further you get in building the framework, the easier it becomes for you to place each individual piece. This phenomenon is true of learning new topics too &amp;mdash; we build cognitive frameworks that make it easier to learn related information. Yet, we don&amp;rsquo;t know much about how language learners use their prior knowledge. We asked, do children with better vocabulary knowledge find it easier to learn new words?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;featured.png&#34; width=&#34;200&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To look at this question, we re-analysed data from five experiments of word learning in children. Each experiment involved teaching children some made-up words (for example, &lt;em&gt;dolpheg&lt;/em&gt;) that were similar to real words in English (&lt;em&gt;dolphin&lt;/em&gt;). Researchers then tested whether the two words became integrated in vocabulary. The integration task measured how quickly the children could detect a short pause inserted into the real words (e.g., &lt;em&gt;dolph__in&lt;/em&gt;), to see whether the made-up words were competing for recognition. When a new word is integrated into vocabulary, response times slow down. The studies each found that sleep was important for this integration to happen: the new words interfered with children’s ability to process real words only when tested the next day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We re-analysed the data from these experiments to look at how word learning might depend on children&amp;rsquo;s prior knowledge. Children’s prior knowledge was assessed using a separate vocabulary test. We found that children with weak prior knowledge were less likely to embed new words into vocabulary overnight. Children with better prior knowledge were more likely to integrate new and known words. So what might be happening differently for these children overnight?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we first learn a new word, a region of the brain called the hippocampus creates a memory of it. It stores information about its sound, its meaning, and its connections to words we know. Those known words are stored in neocortical (outer) regions of the brain. During sleep, new memories are reorganised in the brain so that they too become part of this long-term knowledge. This is achieved by the hippocampus replaying and reactivating the new word memory. As a result, the connections between new and known words become stronger, and the new words become part of long-term vocabulary. We think that children with better prior knowledge can make more connections between new and known words during learning. With more connections, they experience bigger benefits from memory replay during sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Children who have a better language framework seem to more readily lay down each word “piece” of the language puzzle overnight. However, there are many reasons why children who do well at vocabulary assessments might also do well on these measures of word learning. Our research is trying to understand this relationship better. Which aspects of learning benefit most from prior knowledge? Do adults rely on prior knowledge more than children? How can this help us to understand atypical language development? I’ll be addressing these questions in the coming months. By better understanding how children use their existing knowledge during word learning, we hope to better understand why some children lag behind in vocabulary growth. Our finding that existing knowledge supports later &lt;em&gt;integration&lt;/em&gt; of new words into long-term memory tells us that the answer might lie beyond initial vocabulary instruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was a summary of: Consolidation of vocabulary during sleep: The rich get richer? James, Gaskell, Weighall, &amp;amp; Henderson (2017), Neuroscience &amp;amp; Biobehavioral Reviews. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.01.054&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.01.054&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A freely available version can be downloaded here: 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/113350/1/NBB_review_paper.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/113350/1/NBB_review_paper.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sleep‐dependent consolidation in children with comprehension and vocabulary weaknesses: it’ll be alright on the night?</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/jcpp-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/jcpp-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From ZZZs to AAAs: Why Sleep Is an Important Part of Your Study Schedule</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/fym-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/fym-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Offline consolidation supersedes prior knowledge benefits in children&#39;s (but not adults&#39;) word learning</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/devsci-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/devsci-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consolidating new words from repetitive versus multiple stories: Prior knowledge matters</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/jecp-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/jecp-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consolidation of vocabulary during sleep: the rich get richer?</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/nbr-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/nbr-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Commentary: Knowledge Acquisition during Exam Preparation Improves Memory and Modulates Memory Formation</title>
      <link>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/fbn-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.emma-james.co.uk/publication/fbn-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
